<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.7.4">
  <compounddef id="overview_file" kind="page">
    <compoundname>overview_file</compoundname>
    <title>File Classes and Functions</title>
    <detaileddescription>
<para>Classes: <ref refid="classwx_file" kindref="compound">wxFile</ref>, <ref refid="classwx_dir" kindref="compound">wxDir</ref>, <ref refid="classwx_temp_file" kindref="compound">wxTempFile</ref>, <ref refid="classwx_text_file" kindref="compound">wxTextFile</ref></para><para>Functions: see <ref refid="group__group__funcmacro__file" kindref="compound">Files and Directories</ref>.</para><para>wxWidgets provides some functions and classes to facilitate working with files. As usual, the accent is put on cross-platform features which explains, for example, the <ref refid="classwx_text_file" kindref="compound">wxTextFile</ref> class which may be used to convert between different types of text files (DOS/Unix/Mac).</para><para><ref refid="classwx_file" kindref="compound">wxFile</ref> may be used for low-level IO. It contains all the usual functions to work with files (opening/closing, reading/writing, seeking, and so on) but compared with using standard C functions, has error checking (in case of an error a message is logged using <ref refid="classwx_log" kindref="compound">wxLog</ref> facilities) and closes the file automatically in the destructor which may be quite convenient.</para><para><ref refid="classwx_temp_file" kindref="compound">wxTempFile</ref> is a very small file designed to make replacing the files contents safer - see its documentation for more details.</para><para><ref refid="classwx_text_file" kindref="compound">wxTextFile</ref> is a general purpose class for working with small text files on line by line basis. It is especially well suited for working with configuration files and program source files. It can be also used to work with files with &quot;non
native&quot; line termination characters and write them as &quot;native&quot; files if needed (in fact, the files may be written in any format).</para><para><ref refid="classwx_dir" kindref="compound">wxDir</ref> is a helper class for enumerating the files or subdirectories of a directory. It may be used to enumerate all files, only files satisfying the given template mask or only non-hidden files. </para>    </detaileddescription>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
